Guide to the University of Utah AirMed Department video collection 1987-2006
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
University of Utah AirMed Department video collection
1987-2006
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio Visual Archives Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 801-581-8864 http://www.lib.utah.edu/collections/multimedia-archives/
A0010
University of Utah AirMed Depatrment
50 VHS videocassettes, 25 DVDs
The University of Utah AirMed Department video collection (1987-2006) consists of training and safety videos produced and collected by the air medical transport unit of the University of Utah healthcare system as well as coverage relevant to that organization in local and national news broadcasts. The University of Utah's AirMed program was established in 1972.
Historical Note
Eestablished in 1972, the University of Utah's AirMed program was only the eigth such program in the nation. Although AirMed is based at the University of Utah Medical Center in Salt Lake City, Utah, its small fleet of helicopters and turboprop airplanes operate from locations in Salt Lake City, Park City, Orem, Ogden and Rock Springs, Wyoming.
The University of Utah AirMed Department video collection (1987-2006) consists of training and safety videos produced and collected by the air medical transport unit of the University of Utah healthcare system as well as coverage relevant to that organization in local and national news broadcasts. Each of the 50 VHS videocassettes in the collection has been digitized and is available for viewing on one of the 25 DVDs detailed in this finding aid.
The materials arranged alphabetically by subject.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
Donated by University of Utah AirMed Department in 2011.
See also the University of Utah AirMed Department manuscripts collection (Accn 2531).
Utah; Medicine; Helicopter ambulances; Medicine and Health; Moving Images; Moving images; Sound recordings
- Educational part 1, 2000-2001; DVD (Disc 1)
  - A sobering experience, 2000; 2001 (Video 1)
  - Dub for AirMed winter survival training (quality issue), undated (Video 2)
  - Emergency medical directors training, undated (Video 3)
    Overview of Utah emergency medical services (EMS), roles and responsibilities, structuring a quality improvement program.
  - LSTAT: The future is now, undated (Video 4)
  - One for the road, undated (Video 5)
- Educational part 2, 1987-2001; DVD (Disc 2)
  - After the crash, 1987 October 08 (Video 1)
  - Pediatric trauma, 1988 November 11 (Video 2)
  - Stroke/hearing classes, 2001 March 23 (Video 3)
- Emergency services and slideshows, 1997-1999; DVD (Disc 3)
  - AirMed employee slideshow, 1997 (Video 1)
  - AirMed employee slideshow, 1999 (Video 2)
  - In memory of the crews of Lifeguard 71 and AirMed 4, undated (Video 3)
  - Service in memory of Stan Berg, Timothy Hynes, and Shayne Carnahan, undated (Video 4)
- News, 1998-1999; DVD (Disc 4)
  - AirMed helicopter accident, 1998 January 12-17 (Video 1)
  - Miscellaneous news stories, 1998 (Video 2)
  - University of Utah Medical Center helicopters (KTVX 10PM), 1999 July 09 (Video 3)
  - Race car driver Suzie Wells crashes at Rocky Mountain Raceway (KUTV 10PM), 1999 August 21 (Video 4)
- News part 1, 2000; DVD (Disc 5)
  - AirMed helicopter grounded by bird (KUTV, KSTU), 2000 January 06 (Video 1)
  - University of Utah Medical's new AirMed helicopter (KSL, KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2000 January 12 (Video 2)
  - AirMed flight paramedic Eric Troyer (KSL), 2000 February 14 (Video 3)
  - Lehi incident - "Who's in charge?", 2000 May (Video 4)
  - LifeFlight patients in Smithfield wreck (KSL, KTVX), 2000 July 28 (Video 5)
- News part 2, 2000; DVD (Disc 6)
  - Timpanogos Medical Center gets AirMed helicopter, 2000 August 03 (Video 1)
  - Live at University of Utah Hospital/AirMed, 2000 September 05 (Video 2)
  - Hometown hero, paramedic Eric Froerer, 2000 September 05 (Video 3)
  - Timpanogos Medical Center gets AirMed helicopter, 2000 September 19 (Video 1)
- News part 3, 2000; DVD (Disc 7)
  - Willow Creek Mine fire (CNN Headline News), 2000 August 01 (Video 1)
  - AirMed/new safety measures (KTVX), 2000 November 08 (Video 2)
  - Flying with AirMed (KTVX), 2000 November 08 (Video 3)
  - AirMed/Provo Search and Rescue (KUTV), 2000 December 01 (Video 4)
  - Sandra Romero (KUTV), 2000 December 18 (Video 5)
- News part 1, 2001; DVD (Disc 8)
  - University of Utah medical helicopter (KSL, KTVX), 2001 January 04 (Video 1)
  - University of Utah Trauma Center accreditation (KSL, KSTU), 2001 April 27-28 (Video 2)
  - Winter survival training for University of Utah AirMed (KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2001 February 06 (Video 3)
  - Mock driving under the influence (DUI) drill at Skyline High School (KSL, KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2001 April 20 (Video 4)
- News part 2, 2001; DVD (Disc 9)
  - State Road 201 (SR 201) accident (KSL, KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2001 May 11-12 (Video 1)
  - Mock DUI drill at Bingham High School, 2001 May 24 (Video 2)
  - Fatal accident on Interstate 15 (I-15) at 5300 South (KSL, KUTV, KTVX), 2001 May 27 (Video 3)
  - Millcreek Canyon rescue (KSL, KUTV, KTVX), 2001 May 30 (Video 4)
  - AirMed one year (KUTV), 2001 August 02 (Video 5)
- News part 1, 2002; DVD (Disc 10)
  - Train/car accident (KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2002 January 14 (Video 1)
  - AirMed fly Olympic torch (KSTU), 2002 January 20 (Video 2)
  - Flu shots (KTVX), 2002 January 21 (Video 3)
  - CNN American Stories, 2002 February 24 (Video 4)
  - Stroke signs (KTVX), 2002 March 01 (Video 5)
  - Strawberry Reservoir airplane crash (KUTV), 2002 March 16 (Video 6)
- News part 2, 2002; DVD (Disc 11)
  - Dawn Ramsey thanks rescuers (KSL), 2002 April 09 (Video 1)
  - High speed chase - Thomas Tavey (KSL, KUTV, KTVX), 2002 May 02 (Video 2)
  - Butterfield Canyon accident (KSL, KSTU), 2002 September 07 (Video 3)
  - Tooele High School crane accident (KUTV), 2002 September 07 (Video 4)
  - AirMed/Dan Laguna (KUTV), 2002 November 15 (Video 5)
  - West Jordan police shooting (KSL, KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2002 November 18 (Video 6)
- News part 1, 2003; DVD (Disc 12)
  - AirMed responds to LifeFlight crash (KSTU, KUTV), 2003 January 12-13 (Video 1)
  - When seconds count inside the Emergency Room (ER) (KTVX), 2003 February 03 (Video 2)
  - LifeFlight helicopter crash (KUTV), 2003 June 08 (Video 3)
  - LifeFlight crash/University of Utah AirMed (KSTU), 2003 June 09-10 (Video 4)
  - Shooting victim flow to University of Utah Medical Center (KTVX), 2003 November 15 (Video 5)
- News part 2, 2003; DVD (Disc 13)
  - AirMed response - 900 West California Avenue, 2003 June 17 (Video 1)
  - Airplane crash and F-16 SAR footage (419 FW), 2003 October 04 (Video 2)
- News part 1, 2004; DVD (Disc 14)
  - Fog alert medical helicopters (KTVX), 2004 January 12 (Video 1)
  - AirMed survival training (KSL, KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2004 January 17 (Video 2)
  - AirMed night goggles, 2004 February 12 (Video 3)
  - Draper apartment fire/Univeristy of Utah AirMed (KUTV), 2004 November 10 (Video 4)
  - Utah Lake rescue (KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2004 November 26-27 (Video 5)
  - Cold temperatures/AirMed donation (KTVX), 2004 December 23 (Video 6)
- News, 2004-2005; DVD (Disc 15)
  - Draper fire Sky2 footage (KUTV), 2004 November 10 (Video 1)
  - AirMed helps family in accident (KSL, KSTU, KTVX, KUTV), 2005 December 24 (Video 2)
  - AirMed responds (KSL, KUTV, KTVX, KSTU), 2005 May 25 (Video 3)
- Promotional part 1, 1994-2002; DVD (Disc 16)
  - AirMed/Sprint rescue, 1999 (Video 1)
  - Flight for Life salutes EMS, 1994 (Video 2)
  - Hold on to dear life, 1999 (Video 3)
    "Airbag," "ER Doctors," "Troopers," "Kathy and son"
  - University of Utah Hospital Foundation, "It all comes back to you", 2002 August 30 (Video 4)
- Promotional part 2, undated; DVD (Disc 17)
  - AirMed mountain rescue, undated (Video 1)
  - Partners for life, undated (Video 2)
  - St. Mary's LifeFlight final preview, undated (Video 3)
  - University of Utah Hospital Foundation, undated (Video 4)
- Safety part 1, undated; DVD (Disc 18)
  - Air support awareness, undated (Video 1)
  - AirMed/Intermountain Burn Center, undated (Video 2)
  - Kennecott Utah Copper - "Are you ready for work?", undated (Video 3)
  - Fire extinguishers at work, undated (Video 4)
- Safety part 2, undated; DVD (Disc 19)
  - Flight safety philosophy, undated (Video 1)
  - Flight Safety International - recognition of hazardous materials, undated (Video 2)
- Safety part 3, undated; DVD (Disc 20)
  - Helmet information, undated (Video 1)
  - LifeFlight safety operaions - liftoff and landing, undated (Video 2)
  - Scene landing zone safety for helicopters, undated (Video 3)
- Safety part 4, undated; DVD (Disc 21)
  - Evaluating and reporting suspected non-accidental burns, undated (Video 1)
  - The Dark Ages of safety, undated (Video 2)
  - University of Utah Hospital Nursing Service Department - fire safety, undated (Video 3)
- Winter survival training, 1998; DVD (Disc 22)
- Winter survival training, 2000; DVD (Disc 23)
- Winter training and helicopter tape, timecode, 2006 January 12; DVD (Disc 24)
- Miscellaneous videos, 2000-2001; DVD (Disc 25)
  - Kiwi venison, 2001 January 02 (Video 1)
    Deer hunting with a helicopter
  - AirMed helicopter flight, undated (Video 2)
  - Fly-by for Trooper Tom Rittburg, 2000 February 16 (Video 3)
  - Winter 2000, CWH to UMC, multiple stab wounds from state (Video 4)
    Probably Cancer Wellness House (CWH) to University of Utah Medical Center (UMC)